Okay, today's דף daf is קכה, kuf-kaf-hay, 125,
and we are in the middle of מוקצה, muktza, heavily in the
middle of מוקצה muktza and יום טוב, Yom Tov, and we pick
up in the middle of קכד עמוד ב. kuf-kaf-daled amud bais. The
משנה mishna was talking about כלים kelim that broke on שבת, Shabbos,
and there's two ways and there's a debate about whether they have
to be able to do similar to their original work or any
type of work. And there's two ways of reading it. Is it
better if they broke, it might say broke on שבת, Shabbos, but
the question is, that's the question. The first approach of the גמרא
Gemara is if they broke on שבת Shabbos it's better because then
they started שבת Shabbos being מוכן, muchan, being fit to be used
and not in the מוקצה muktza category. But the new approach of
the גמרא Gemara is that no, if it breaks on שבת Shabbos
it creates a נולד nolad issue, and it's better if it broke
ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. תני חדא, tanya chada,
the line starts with the word מסיקין. masikin. It's about fifteen lines
from the bottom, starts with the word מסיקין. masikin. תני חדא מסיקין
בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים. tanya chada masikin bekelim ve'ein masikin beshivrei
kelim.
One ברייתא beraita says that on יום טוב Yom Tov you can
burn vessels but not vessels that have broken, which is presumably what
you would want to be burning. ותני אידך, vetanya idach, another ברייתא
beraita says כשם שמסיקין בכלים כך מסיקין בשברי כלים. kesheim shemasikin bekelim
kach masikin beshivrei kelim. The same way you can burn vessels, you
can burn broken vessels. ותני אידך, vetanya idach, and we have a
third ברייתא beraita that says אין מסיקין לא בכלים ולא בשברי כלים.
ein masikin lo bekelim velo beshivrei kelim. You can't burn either. So
we have three out of the four logical possibilities. What can you
burn? Wood! Wood! Okay, so how do you reconcile this? הא רבי
יהודה, ha Reb Yehuda, the one that's a רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda
is of the position that he holds of נולד. nolad. So he
says you can burn כלים kelim because they're not מוקצה, muktza, but
something that broke on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב Yom Tov rather
is נולד, nolad, so you can't use שברי כלים, shivrei kelim, broken
כלים. kelim. הא רבי שמעון, ha Reb Shimon, רבי שמעון Reb Shimon
is very lenient and he doesn't hold of the concept of נולד,
nolad, so you can even use a כלי kli that broke on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now how about the one that says you
can't even use normal כלים kelim to burn? So, could have said
it's בל תשחית, bal tashchis, but no, presumably יום טוב Yom Tov
concerned, so הא רבי נחמיה. ha Reb Nechemia. That's our classic רבי
נחמיה Reb Nechemia who's always a good position when you for a
very restrictive approach, and he says you can only use a כלי
kli for its intended purpose. So a כלי kli is not intended,
its intended purpose is not firewood, and a שבר כלי shever kli
presumably is נולד. nolad. So you're stuck either way.
Good point, and I also, let's say I said, you know, if
it breaks I'll use it for firewood and I said that before,
would that be okay?
No, intended purpose means the purpose not what's in your mind but
what objectively is it state, not mean your intention, meaning the purpose
it's made for. אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, הני לבני דאשתייר
מבניינא, hanei livnei de'ishtayer mibinyana, if you have bricks that were left
over from out of like from a construction, bricks on a construction
site, שרי לטלטולינהו, shari letaltulinhu, you can move them, which is pretty
shocking. You would think that they'd be מוקצה. muktza. Why? דחזו למיסמך
עלייהו. dechazu lemismach aleihu. They are fit to sit on. Now this
is going to be an important question which is something that's not
a כלי kli
and that maybe has a use. Theoretically, what do you need to
make it into a כלי? kli? Like your old using a rock
as a paperweight. Okay, so this sounds like, you know, the fact
that maybe it would be a common thing, you got a pile
of bricks left over, people would walk by, they'd sit on it.
Okay, presumably it doesn't mean just theoretically because then how you know,
but who knows? Anyway, this is going to be a discussion that
we're going to see at the end of today as well, which
is what do you need to turn something that's basically a brick,
a stone, into a כלי? kli? So he says that you don't
need anything, but most it's the fact that the context is enough
that it would be a normal usage of it. Let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
שרגינהו ודאי אקצינהו, sharginhu vadai aktsinhu, however if you stacked them up,
then definitely it's clear that you are putting them aside, you're making
them מוקצה muktza because you want to use them for the next
construction. Okay, so but if it's without doing an act to push
them away, actually naturally they're considered not מוקצה, muktza, which is quite
surprising and we're going to hear other opinions on a similar topic
that are going to demand much more.
Do you want to say something Charlie?
Yeah, if I'm moving them to create something I can sit on,
that feels like
בונה.
boneh. Yeah but you're not necessarily, well first of all that's an
interesting question. Are stacking things that are not, don't connect in any
way and just are stacked, you know, probably would not be בונה
boneh unless you're making like an אהל ohel or something. But anyway
we're not even necessarily talking about that. We might be just talking
about, you know... Oh I see, because you're saying if you're moving
them and they're separate bricks, you're not just moving one or
two, you're moving... Yeah, but you know it's probably not בונה boneh
because it's again, they're not, they're not interlocking in any way and
it's not an אהל. ohel. But it's a, yeah.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues,
similar discussions about things that are like שברי כלים shivrei kelim or
things, you know, and whether they are מוקצה muktza or not. So
אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, חרס קטנה,
cheres ketana, if you have a little piece of pottery, again it's
a שבר
כלי, shever kli, מותר לטלטלה בחצר, mutar letaltala bechatzer, so you can
move it in a חצר. chatzer. Presum... presumably this means let's say
that it broke ערב שבת, erev shabbos, we're not dealing with the
נולד nolad issue.
You can move it. When is it considered to be ראוי, roy,
which is basically going back to our משנה, mishna, when it's in
the courtyard because then it's a type of thing that people would
use. אבל בכרמלית, Aval bekarmelis, if it's out in a כרמלית, karmelis,
לא, lo, you can't move it even if you're moving it within
ארבע אמות arba amos because, in a courtyard you have a lot
of activity that's done and maybe you often have broken pottery because
people are using their pottery in a courtyard. So therefore in that
context it's a type of thing that you could imagine using. But
out in the כרמלית karmelis it doesn't have that same- so
this חצר chatzer is an עירוב, eruv, right?
Yeah, this חצר chatzer is something you can carry in. No, it's
a מוקצה muktzeh issue, it's not a carrying issue. כרמלית karmelis you
can't move it even within ארבע אמות. arba amos. So again it's
going back to the question of when is something again like a
rock or like a שבר כלי, shever kli, when is it considered
to be מוכן muchan and not
מוקצה, muktzeh, what makes it that and not garbage? So to some
degree the answer is context. So he says only the context of
being in a חצר. chatzer.
So this doesn't really make a difference if there actually was a
כלי kli at the time but since there's usually כלים, kelim, right,
that's why if you find this שבר כלי shever kli it's okay?
No, what do you mean?
You said the reason why it's okay in a חצר chatzer because
there's usually כלים- kelim no,
no, no, because there are things, yeah, because in this context it
normally is a type of thing that people do pick this up
and use it and so on.
Right, so even if there wasn't actually something to use it for?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Nachman amar
Shmuel, so that's what he says. ורב נחמן דידיה אמר, veRav Nachman
didey amar, רב נחמן Rav Nachman himself says אפילו בכרמלית, afilu bekarmelis,
you
even in a כרמלית karmelis you can use it, in that context
it's still the type of thing that people would pick up and
use. אבל ברשות הרבים, Aval birshus harabbim, in a major thoroughfare, לא,
lo,
then is not in a context where people or these things are
normally found or where people would normally use them. ורבא אמר אפילו
ברשות הרבים, VeRava amar afilu birshus harabbim, even in a public domain
again without carrying it ארבע אמות arba amos but it's a מוקצה
muktzeh question. So here the real question is what context makes something
not a כלי, kli, makes it in the category of yeah yeah
it's a type of thing that people will use, it's considered to
be a כלי. kli. Okay, ואזדא רבא לטעמיה, veazda Rava litaameh,
רבא Rava goes according to his reasoning, דרבא הוה קאזיל בריטקא deRava
hava ka'azil beRitka דמחוזא, deMechuza,
רבא Rava was going in ריטקא Ritka which רש"י Rashi says is
the name of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim דמחוזא deMechuza
which was his city. אטווסא מסאניה, itvassa masaneh,
thank you Tina, his shoes got dirty with mud. אתא שמעיה, ata
shamayeh, so his assistant came, his attendant came, שקל חספא, shakal chaspa,
picked up a piece of pottery from the road in the middle
of רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, again not walking with it just right
there, without moving, וקא מכפר ליה, veka mechaper leh,
and he started scraping רבא's Rava shoe for him. רבו בני רבנן
עליה, Ravu bnei rabbanan aleh, so all the rabbinical students started yelling
at him, hey, שבת, shabbos, you can't pick up a piece of
pottery! אמר, Amar, so then רבא Rava said, coming to the defense
of his attendant, לא מסתייה דלא גמרי, lo mistayei dlo gamri,
to these rabbinical students, he said it's not enough that you don't
know the הלכה, halacha, אלא מגמר נמי מגמרי, ela migmar nami migmri,
you're trying to teach the wrong הלכה halacha to people? Is it
not enough that you're ignorant but you have to proclaim your ignorance?
So give my guy a break. אילו בחצר הוי, Ilu bachatzer havai,
if we were in a חצר, chatzer, מי לא חזי לכסויי בי
מנא, mi lo chazi lechasuyei bei mana,
then everybody would agree that a pottery shard is okay, a שבר
כלי, shever kli, that's essentially our משנה, mishna, because you could use
it to cover a vessel, you could find uses for it in
a חצר, chatzer, common uses.
הכא נמי, Hacha nami, given it's in a
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, חזי לדידי, chazi ledidi, I have a use
for it. So the fact that it's not often used in רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, basically he says and this is helpful because as
opposed to the earlier opinion that says you need a particular context,
what רבא Rava is saying, if it's in some contexts it's ראוי,
roy, then that makes it considered ראוי roy in all contexts, okay,
as long as under some maybe common circumstances this type of thing
would be considered not מוקצה muktzeh then wherever context you find it
in if you have a use for it that's fine.
Doesn't it go the other way around right? If in some contexts
it's not ראוי roy then?
Right, it's always true. If in some contexts it's ראוי roy then
in others it's not, okay, but the point is as long as
it's ראוי roy in some, now again that some might have to
be the majority of cases, it's not exactly clear, but that's enough,
okay? So this is the question of something that's not a כלי,
kli, what you need, what type of context you need to make
it not מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues similar
discussions about things that are like שבר כלים shever kelim and whether
they are מוקצה muktzeh or not. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, מגופת חבית שנכתתה, megufas chavis shenichtesa, if you
have a cover of a barrel and the barrel has been shattered,
מותר לטלטלה בשבת, mutar letaltla b'shabbos,
you can move the cover, you can move the shattered pieces of
the barrel. It's basically the same idea of a שבר כלי. shever
kli. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it was taught similarly: מגופה
שנכתתה, Megufa shenichtesa,
a cover and apparently רש"י Rashi says it means the barrel has
been shattered, היא ושבריה, hi ushvareha, it and the broken pieces of
the barrel, מותר לטלטלה
בשבת. mutar letaltla b'shabbos. So again doesn't seem to be much of
a חידוש. chiddush. ולא יספוס ממנה שבר לכסות בה כלי, V'lo yispus
mimena shever lechasos bo kli,
but you shouldn't break from this barrel or from a part of
a broken part another, break off a piece to use to cover,
then it's like making a vessel on שבת, shabbos, it's like cutting
something, making something and so on. רש"י Rashi says it doesn't only
mean not to break off a piece, it means like don't smooth
the edges of the piece, that's even worse and it's really like
you're making it into a vessel. Okay, וליסמוך בה כרעי המטה, velismoch
boh karei hamita, or to use it to support a bed. ואם
זרקה באשפה, Ve'im zarka b'ashpa, but if you took this broken barrel
and threw it in the garbage, אסורה, asura, then it's forbidden. So
again this is the question. That a broken piece of a כלי,
kli, since it has some use, is considered not to be מוקצה.
muktzeh. Okay, but here the context can make it, can make it
מוקצה. muktzeh. The normal context is it's okay, the normal assumption, but
if you throw it out, then you've defined it as garbage, then
it is מוקצה. muktzeh. So because it has no use. Has no
use, right. Exactly. So מתקיף לה רב פפא, matkif lah Rav Pappa,
one minute, רב פפא Rav Pappa asked, אלא מעתה, ela meatah, really?
If that's true,
זרקה לגלימיה, zarkeh liglimeh, if you threw your coat out, הכא נמי
דאסור, hacha nami deasur, does that make it מוקצה? muktzeh? אלא אמר
רב פפא, ella amar Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said,
no, it's not throwing it out on שבת, Shabbos, וזרקה מבעוד יום
לאשפה, uzerakah mibod yom laashpah, but if you threw it out ערב
שבת, erev Shabbos, then it's אסור. asur. So of course you could
say, and if you threw your coat out ערב שבת, erev Shabbos,
is it אסור? asur? So it says, okay, but there already we
understand a difference, meaning, we understand that this thing, whether it's defined
as usable or garbage, has a lot to do with how you're
going to treat it. But so if when שבת Shabbos came in,
you already treated it as garbage, then it never is, then it's
defined as garbage. Okay, and then for everyone. If you're the owner,
then for everyone, presumably. Okay, it's a good question though. But if
it's something that really is a כלי, kli, just throwing it out
doesn't make it stop being a כלי. kli. Okay, so that we,
but at least we understand that that can work if it's ערב
שבת. erev Shabbos. But if it's on שבת, Shabbos, and it started
שבת Shabbos usable, switching the context on שבת, Shabbos, throwing it out
on שבת Shabbos won't redefine it. Okay, but the basic פשט pshat
of all of this is that our משנה Mishnah says a broken
part of a vessel is considered to be not מוקצה. muktzeh. The
גמרא Gemara is trying to get a handle on it and trying
to explain because it's a case where the common context would be
that it would be usable. Asks a question about what if in
a particular context it's not, like in a רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim?
Do you go by the חצר chatzer or do you go by
the specific context it's found in? Then it asks the question about
well, what if you did something to make it clear you weren't
interested in it, like throwing it out? So גמרא Gemara says okay,
that would be different, then it would be מוקצה muktzeh if you
throw it out before שבת. Shabbos. If you throw it on שבת,
Shabbos, then it would retain its status. So the גמרא Gemara here
is qualifying these cases of שבר כלי. shever kli. I should also
say though that שבר כלי shever kli is presumably, although the גמרא
Gemara hasn't said this black and white, is presumably better than a
random stick or stone, because at least this started as a כלי.
kli. So it started as a type of a thing that was,
you know, an object that you use, that's part of the things
that you know, so therefore you don't necessarily discard them so easily
and they remain within the context of types of things you might
use. Okay, the presumption is that a random stick or stone from
the, you know, that you would find would require more to make
it not מוקצה muktzeh and wouldn't sort of hold on to its,
to its sort of usable status because it never had a usable
status to begin with. Okay, and we're going to see that a
little bit, we saw it already a little bit about bricks, but
bricks I should say is also better than a stick and stone.
A brick is at least made to be used, it's an artifact,
it's not a random piece of nature. Okay, so how much do
you need for something that's just like that, that again, is, is,
is, even starts off with not under human control, you know, and
not a human artifact, to make that something that's considered מוכן, muchan,
but we will see that a little bit later today. Yes, רבקה?
Rivka?
Just a very side comment on this servant of רבה Rabbah
accompanying רבה Rabbah on a שבת Shabbos walk. Right. Isn't he keeping
שבת? Shabbos? Yeah, the servant.
Sure. He has to keep שבת. Shabbos. Sure.
So why is he cleaning off רבה's Rabbah shoes?
He should have cleaned off his own shoes. I mean.
Oh, your question is just is he keeping in the שבת Shabbos
spirit.
Did most of these rabbis have servants? He was just, it was
שבת.
Shabbos. Right, I understand.
And he's got this servant on the floor.
I understand. But but,
yes, but okay, so so what's bothering you is the is not
the חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, but it's the sense of servitude on
שבת. Shabbat.
He has a servant and he shouldn't be walking, he shouldn't be.
I don't understand. If I hire somebody, a Jewish babysitter on שבת,
Shabbat, and I'm walking to שול shul and there's an עירוב, eruv,
and they're pushing the carriage and every time my kid cries or
whatever they're feeding it and changing the diaper and this and that,
is that okay or not okay?
This was not that kind of a necessity.
This wasn't
slavery, to use somebody's being paid to be in attendance.
To walk next to him.
Yeah. But if I'm not paying somebody to push my baby and
change the diapers?
Do we assume most of these rabbis had personal?
I don't know, we definitely find often, we find often
that they did. I assume a lot of it had to do
with as Charlie says, the wealth.
Was רבה Rabbah wealthy?
I don't know, he was in a wealthy city, he was in
מחוזא. Mechuza. A long time ago? What?
Maybe he was elderly?
Maybe he was elderly, right.
We say the same thing, we don't necessarily say the same thing
as food, right? Like let's say there's like some part that, you
know, and you want to throw it out, "Hey, what are you
throwing that out for? Like, you know, I want to eat it."
Like, you know, does that make it מוקצה muktzeh for me?
Well, again, throwing it out on שבת Shabbos as we've seen doesn't
really change the status,
so the really, if, so the גמרא's Gemara really, it's only throwing
stuff out ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So that is an interesting question,
let's say ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, you know, here's, here's an example,
ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, my wife is cleaning up and she throws
the Friday New York Times into the, you know, into the garbage,
and I haven't had a chance to read it yet. Can I...
go pull it out of the garbage on שבת. Shabbos. So okay,
that's a question. I think that basically the message here is that
something that basically is a clearly a כלי, kli, like a גלימא,
glima, doesn't get lose its status even when it's thrown out, okay,
but something that is more ambiguous status like the broken pieces of
pottery lose its
status as paper just because she threw it out. Exactly. Yeah. Are
there some substance between carrying on שבת Shabbos versus the מוקצה Muktzah
in terms of use?
Like כרמלית karmelis versus רשות הרבים reshus harabbim issue?
Well, before we had like if it's small enough that you're not
going to— it's not functional at all, then it's not considered an
איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraisa to carry it.
Yeah. Even in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
Right, I mean there were שיעורים shiurim for carrying, yeah.
Right, but do we find some for מוקצה? Muktzah? No, no.
I thought you were saying is maybe the difference of כרמלית karmelis
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim was since we said מוקצה Muktzah is tied
to carrying maybe we have stricter rules of מוקצה Muktzah in רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim, but we definitely don't find this. This is all
very much in the context of שברים shavarim and about whether they're
considered to be usable or not. Yeah, last question then we have
to move. Yeah.
It doesn't explicitly states these— these shards
whether they were broken on שבת Shabbat or not.
Right, the גמרא Gemara is bracketing that. I think it's assuming that
on שבת Shabbat breaks is no-fly issues and we're going to be
working with the assumption that it was broken before שבת. Shabbat. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר מר בר המדורא אמר שמואל, Amar Mar Bar Hamdura amar Shmuel,
קרומי דמחצלת kromei d'machatzeles מותר לטלטלם בשבת. mutar l'taltelan b'Shabbos. If you
have again, this is like a שבר כלי, shever kli, you have
a— a strand used from a like a reed mat. So one
of the— I don't know what— I don't know what to call
it, anyway, one of the straps has come out— not straps, but
you know, one of the things that you weave into it, reeds,
yeah. Anyway, מותר לטלטלם בשבת, mutar l'taltelan b'Shabbos, you can move it.
Again, it's like a— like a שבר כלי. shever kli. So מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? אמר רב, Amar Rav, סבורא סבורא אמר בר המדורא
אסברה לי, savora savora amar Bar Hamdura asbarah li, בר המדורא Bar
Hamdura is the one that said this explained it to me. מחצלת
גופא למאי חזי? Machatzeles gufah l'mai chazei? What do you can use
a mat for other than sitting on it? לכסויי בי עפרא, L'chasuyei
bei afra, to cover dirt, so like if there's something יחיד yachid
on the ground or you don't want the dirt to rise up.
So הני נמי חזו לכסויי בי טינופת, hani nami chazu l'chasuyei bei
tinofes, you can use even a piece of little strap to cover
some— some filth. So basically it's not only doing מעין מלאכה, me'ein
melacha, it could even do מעין מלאכתן, me'ein melachtan, it could be
similar to the original use, which is even a more restrictive approach.
אמר רבי זירא אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav,
שירי פרוזמות shirei pruzmos אסור לטלטלם
בשבת. assur l'taltelan b'Shabbos. So a פרוזמא pruzma is a— is like
a garment and the— and so this is basically— what do you
call it? Like the remnants of the garment, you can't move them
on שבת. Shabbos. So why not? Why isn't that just a שבר
כלי? shever kli? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, במטלוניות שאין בה ג'
על ג'. b'matlaniyos she'ein bah gimmel al gimmel. We're talking about a
little swath of the garment that doesn't even have three by three.
It's— you know, fingers— fingers big. דלא חזי לא לעניים ולא לעשירים.
d'lo chazi lo l'aniyim v'lo l'ashirim. It can—
it's not used not only by rich people, even poor people won't
use it, it's not even big enough to be a patch. And
presumably it's not big enough to do really anything functional with. So
when it gets to a side of a שבר כלי, shever kli,
again, this is an example of it's not doing מעין מלאכה, me'ein
melacha, it doesn't have a reasonable use to do with it as
a
שבר כלי. shever kli. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, שירי תנור ישן
shirei tanur yashan הרי הן ככל הכלים harei hen k'chol hakelim הניטלין
בחצר, hani-talin b'chatzer, mean it's— it's not מוקצה, Muktzah, it's a שבר
כלי. shever kli. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, אין ניטלין,
ein nitlin, you can't use it. העיד רבי יוסי משום רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב He'id Rabbi Yossi mishum Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov על שירי
תנור ישן שניטלין בשבת. al shirei tanur yashan she'nitlin b'Shabbos. So— so
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi testified in the name of רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you
can move them. So here we have a debate of using the
broken pieces of a oven that was essentially made out of pottery,
okay? ועל כיסויו, v'al kisuyo, and not only that, the cover of
an oven because an oven basically was like a big pot. It
was like a huge type of a, you know, huge sort of
like, you know, think of like what those— called? Like a stockpot,
except much larger, okay? It was connected to the ground. You'd put
a fire in the bottom and you'd put basically and you'd put
a pot into the pot.
Right, so a תנור tanur looked like this, okay, it would be
connected to the ground, it would be— would have like plaster keeping
it in the ground, you put a fire— you put your fire
here, and you put your pot on top, and you could have
a cover like on top of the oven.
Okay? So that's your oven. Okay? So he said the cover to
the oven can be carried on שבת Shabbat שאינו צריך בית יד
she'eino tzarich beis yad even if it does not have a handle.
So we'll worry about the handle and the cover in a minute.
Let's first talk about the oven. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? What is
the debate about the shattered pieces of the oven? So אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, so says אביי, Abaye, בעושין מעין מלאכה ואין עושין מעין
מלאכתן קמיפלגי. b'osin me'ein melacha v'ein osin me'ein melachtan kamifligi. something that—
that things
that do a type of a function but not their original function.
Meaning so you have a broken piece of an oven that you
can use for something, you can use, I don't know, to cover—
to cover a vessel, but you can't use it as an oven.
It's a broken piece of pottery. So it can— it's functional but
not its original
function. ורבי יהודה לטעמיה ורבי מאיר לטעמיה. v'Rabbi Yehuda l'ta'amei v'Rabbi Meir
l'ta'amei. And this is the debate in the משנה. Mishnah. The debate
in the משנה, Mishnah, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says as long
as it does some function and רבי יהודה— Rabbi Yehuda which and
often the silent תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. especially when the opposing voice
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* is assumed to be רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. So therefore, it can, so as long
as it does some function, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
says it has to do similar to the original function, so a
very simple debate. We assume the broken pieces of the oven can
do a function but not a baking or cooking function. So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says it's fine and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* says it's מוקצה muktseh *Muktzah*. Very simple, a very
simple explanation. So מתקיף לה רבא *Maskif la Rava*, so רבא *Rava*
asked on this, אי ei הכי hachi *ee hachi*, if that's the
debate, דמפלגי בשיבי תנורא *de-miflegi be-shivei tannura*, why are you arguing on
the broken pieces of an oven? לפלגו בשיבי כלים בעלמא *Liflegu be-shivei
kelim be-alma*, argue about normal broken pieces of a vessel. Now that's
only a good question if you have a good answer because your
normal answer point is: What do you mean? It's just applying this
issue to a practical case. Okay, but the reason it's a strong
question is because we're going to see that רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* and רבי Rabbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* have another debate about ovens.
So רבא *Rava* is saying the fact that they're debating about ovens
in particular suggests that it's not a generic debate, that it's specific
about ovens because there's another place that רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
and רבי Rabbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* debate about ovens. So let's take
a look. אלא אמר amar רבא *Ela amar Rava*, so said רבא
*Rava*, בשיבי דהאי תנורא קא מפלגי *be-shivei de-hai tannura ka miflegi*, they're
debating about the broken pieces of a very particular oven. Not the
תנור של shel עכנאי *Tannur shel Achnai*, don't get too excited. Okay,
דתנן detnan, *detnan*, that we taught in the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* in
כלים *Kelim*, נתנו על פי הבור או על פי הדות *natno al
pi ha-bor o al pi ha-dut*, you took your oven, your big
pottery oven, and rather than plastering it to the ground, you put
it into a hole, you put it into a well. Okay, so
you inserted it into a well, ונתן שם אבן *ve-natan sham even*,
and you put a stone there. So basically the way רש״י Rashi
*Rashi* explains it, and רמב״ם *Rambam* explains it a little bit differently,
is that
here is your oven,
but rather than plastering it to the ground, you inserted your oven
into a well. Here's your well. Okay, now what did you do
to keep it tight? You don't want there to be, first of
all, you want it to stay steady, you don't want there to
be air space so that the heat doesn't get out, right? Because
basically רש״י Rashi *Rashi* also says there's not really a floor to
the oven, you're going to put your fire in the well. So
what you did here is, he says that it's really the walls
of the well are very close to the walls of the oven,
and you put a rock here to sort of keep it tight,
like you wedge little stones in to keep it tight, but it's
very close to the walls of the oven. And because it's really
a nice tight fit and the heat really goes straight into the
oven and doesn't like escape, then it's considered like it is plastered
to the ground. Okay, that's as good as being plastered to the
ground, because one of the הלכות *halakhot* of an oven for טומאה
וטהרה *tumah ve-taharah* is that it only becomes טמא *tammei*, ironically, if
it's plastered to the ground. Normally things connected to the ground are
טהור *tahor*, but for an oven, we're going to see in a
minute, its status as an oven to become טמא *tammei* is only
if it's connected to the ground. So the idea is this, which
is a tight fit and small rocks are helping to keep it
tight, that's considered connected to the ground and טמא *tammei*. Is your
hand raised or is it just for health purposes? Not because you
have a question. Okay, so let's take a look. נתנו על פי
הבור או על פי הדות *natno al pi ha-bor o al pi
ha-dut*, by the well or by the דות *dut* which is a
well with like a structure around it, ונתן שם אבן *ve-natan sham
even*, and you put a rock between, you know, there to keep
it tight. רבי Rabbi יהודה אומר omer *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, אם im
מסיק מלמטה והוא ניסוק מלמעלה *im masik milmata ve-hu nisok milmala*, if
you light a fire at the bottom of the well and the
oven gets like really heated up at the top,
so the heat gets contained, then טמא *tammei*. Then it's like it's
connected to the ground and then it's a classic oven and then
it can become טמא *tammei*. ואם לאו ve'im lav, *ve-im lav*, but
if heat escapes around the sides, then it's like it's not connected
to the ground and טהור *tahor*. וחכמים אומרים *ve-Chachamim omrim*, and the
sages say, which would here be the רבי Rabbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
presumably is the one who argues on רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, הוא
והוא סק מכל מקום *hu ve-hu sak mikol makom*, it doesn't matter,
once it's heated up, then טמא *tammei*, then it's considered an oven
and it doesn't matter if some heat escapes. ובמאי קמיפלגי *uv'mai kamiflegi*,
or it doesn't, right, it doesn't matter if it's considered connected to
the ground is really the point. ובמאי קמיפלגי *uv'mai kamiflegi*, what do
they debate? בהאי קרא *be-hai kra*, the following verse. תנור וכירים יותץ
טמאים הם *Tannur ve-khirayim yutatz temeim hem*, an oven and a כירה
*kirah*, another type of oven, shall be shattered, they are טמא *tammei*.
If they come in contact with something טמא *tammei*, טמאים יהיו לכם
*temeim yihyu lachem*, they shall be טמא *tammei* to you. רבי יהודה
סבר *Rabbi Yehuda savar*, now the key word here is יותץ *yutatz*.
That יותץ *yutatz* is a word to like demolish, which suggests something
is connected to the ground. A vessel, the word would be שבירה
*shevirah*, to break. But יותץ *yutatz* is demolish, it's a word you
have for something connected to the ground, like a building or an
oven connected to the ground. So from here we learn that as
again, as opposed to all other things which become טמא *tammei* more
when they are disconnected, an oven becomes is considered an oven to
become טמא *tammei* only if it's connected to the ground. So that's
the position of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי יהודה סבר מחוסר נתיצה
טמא *Rabbi Yehuda savar mechusar netitza tammei*, only something that lacks being
shattered, that it's possible to talk about sort
of demolishing can become טמא *tammei*. Only something connected to the ground,
an oven, will become טמא *tammei*.
שאין מחוסר נתיצה טהור *she-ein mechusar netitza tahor*, something that was not
in that category is טהור *tahor*, is not an oven and therefore
is טהור *tahor*. ורבנן סברי *ve-Rabbanan savri*, the rabbis hold, טמאים יהיו
לכם מכל מקום *temeim yihyu lachem mikol makom*, the end of. The
end of the verse says they will be טמא *tamei* for you,
which is a more inclusive statement, means regardless, I don't care connected
or not connected. ורבנן נמי *ve-rabbanan nami*, הכתיב יותץ *ha-ketiv yutatz*? One
minute, what do they deal with the idea that uses the verb
יותץ *yutatz*, which suggests connected to the ground? הוא לאידך גיסא *hu
le-idach gisa*. No, that's not to tell you that you need to
be connected. That's to tell you the opposite point. דסלקא דעתך אמינה
*de-salka da'atach amina*, this is what we were saying, I would have
thought כיון דחבריה בארעא *keivan de-chavrei be-ara*, if since you connected it
to the ground, כגופא דארעא דמי *ke-gufa de-ara dami*, it's like it's
part of the ground, it's like normal things that are connected and
that it cannot become טמא *tamei*, קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*
that it can. So the Rabbis say I don't need an oven
to be connected to the ground to be טמא *tamei*. The use
of the word יותץ *yutatz* is saying even if it's connected to
the ground it'll become טמא *tamei*, but not that you need that.
ואידך נמי *ve-idach nami*, now Rabbi Yehuda who says you need it
connected to the ground, הכתיב טמאים יהיו לכם *ha-ketiv tamei'im yihyu lachem*,
don't you have a more general verse they shall be טמא *tamei*
to you, which sounds like it's a more inclusive, a bigger category?
היא כרב יהודה משמואל *hi ke-rav Yehuda mi-Shmuel*. No, that's telling me
like רב Rav, יהודה משמואל *rav Yehuda mi-Shmuel*. דאמר damar רב Rav
יהודה משמואל מחלוקת בהיסק ראשון *de-amar rav Yehuda mi-Shmuel machlokes be-heseik rishon*.
This idea that it needed to be connected to the ground was
only the first time it was fired up, because the first time
an oven is fired up is when the pottery that the oven
is made out of gets hardened and that's where it gets its
identity, the first time it's fired up. So the approach that says
it needs to be connected to the ground to be an oven
is only at that first firing up of it when it's defined
and gets its identity. אבל aval היסק שני *aval heseik sheini*, if
afterwards you detached it and now you're firing it up a second
time, then everybody agrees it does not have to be attached. אפילו
afilu תלוי בצואר גמל *afillu talui be-tzavar gamal*, even if it's suspended
from the neck of a camel, interesting image, it would still be
considered טמא *tamei*. So basically we are saying that there's a debate
that Rabbi Yehuda says an oven is only defined as an oven
if it's attached to the ground at the time when it's first
fired up and therefore he defines it requires when it's in this
hole to be in a very particular configuration so it's defined as
connected to the ground. That's what they're debating. Okay now. Yes, let
me just read one more sentence. אמר עולא בהיסק ראשון לרבנן *amar
Ulla be-heseik rishon le-rabbanan*, and just to make it clear the Rabbis
have no requirement of being attached, so meaning Rabbi Meir, so even
in the first firing up אפילו תלוי בצואר גמל *afillu talui be-tzavar
gamal*, even suspended from the neck of a camel, so it would
still be טמא *tamei*. So the whole debate is that do you
need for an oven to be טמא *tamei* it to be attached
to the ground at the time when it is first fired up?
Yes. Maybe they're just speaking figuratively, there's not really a hanging oven
around the neck of a camel? I would hope not. Okay, right.
Why they use that as an image I don't know. Now, how
does that explain the debate? So presumably what we're saying is you
got this thing which was not attached to the ground when it
was fired up, so Rabbi Yehuda basically feels that that's not really
an oven, so it's not really a כלי kli. *kli*, assuming that
you use טומאה וטהרה *tumah ve-tahara* definitions to apply to שבת Shabbat,
*Shabbos*, so therefore it is what do you call it, it is
מוקצה muktseh *muktzah*. And the Rabbis hold it is an oven, it
is a כלי kli *kli*, and therefore if you have broken parts
of it it's not מוקצה muktseh *muktzah*. Again, assuming that these very
technical טומאה וטהרה *tumah ve-tahara* issues should be relevant for שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos* definitions of מוקצה muktseh *muktzah* or not. So that's how he
wants to explain it, but at least it ties into an oven
and to another debate of Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Meir by an
oven. So רב אשי *rav Ashi* does not like this. מתקיף לה
רב אשי *maskif la rav Ashi*, רב אשי *rav Ashi* asked on
that, אי הכי *i hachi*, if that's what they're debating, אדמיפלגי בשברי
תנור *ade-mifligi be-shivrei tanur*, why if they're debating broken parts of an
oven, ליפלגי בתנור גופא *lifligi be-tanur gufa*? They should debate the oven
itself because that's a more fundamental debate, that one says it's a
כלי kli, *kli* and one says it's not a כלי kli *kli*
according to you. השתא תנור גופא לרבי יהודה לא lo הוי מנא
*hashata tanur gufa le-rabbi Yehuda lo havei mana*, if the oven itself,
since it was not fired up when it was connected to the
ground, is not considered a vessel, מה שבריו מיבעיא *ma shevarav mi-ba'ya*?
Is there any question about its broken pieces? So if they're talking
about broken pieces it is not a big question about ovens in
general. אלא אמר רב אשי לעולם כדאמרינן מעיקרא *ela amar rav Ashi
le-olam ke-d'amrinan mei-ikara*, it's like we said originally, which is certainly the
easier reasoning, that they're having the same debate in the משנה mishnah.
*mishnah* about broken pieces of a vessel that cannot do similar to
their original function. So why are we talking specifically about an oven?
Because it's, here's the case: ובאותה מעשה maiseh טפקא *u-ve-osa ma'aseh tafka*.
It can make, it can be used for טפקא *tafka*, I don't
know exactly what the word means but רש״י *Rashi* describes it to
mean that you can use it by basically like a type of
a guess a grill, though that's not technically the point. But the
point is as opposed to an oven where you put the fire
inside and the walls contain the heat, here what can you use
this little piece for? You can put a fire under it and
this little piece gets hot and you put something on top of
it. Okay, so works more of like what, like a stovetop rather
than an oven. What, like a בלטה *blata*? Right, okay, so here
you can use it more like a stovetop rather than an oven,
and that's the issue. Is that considered enough like its original function
or not? רבי מאיר לדברי דרבי יהודה קאמר *rabbi Meir le-divrei de-rabbi
Yehuda ka'mar*, Rabbi Meir is making an argument that Rabbi Yehuda at
least should concede to this case. לדידי *le-didi*, as far as I'm
concerned, even in those... It didn’t mean מלאכה. I don’t care that
it’s any type of function it can do, it doesn’t have to
be the original function. אלא לדידך, Ella ledidach, according to you, מודי
לי מיהא דחריבא מלאכתה הוה. modee li miha decharyava melachta hava hoo.
Admit to me at least that this thing is similar enough to
its original function. רבי יהודה, רבי יהודה says back, לא דמי, lo
dami, it’s not comparable. התם הסקה מבפנים הכא הסקה מבחוץ. Hasam haseka
mibifnim hacha haseka mibachutz. In one case the fire is on the
inside, in this case the fire is on the outside. התם באומד,
Hasam be'umad, in the first case the things are sort of standing
up when they're in the oven. הכא לאו באומד, Hacha lav be'umad,
here the things you’re putting on the fire, you’re putting them sort
of flat down on the ground on the floor, rather than suspended
up in the oven. So it’s not enough like the original thing.
So the upshot of all of this is, you have broken vessels.
If they break on שבת, Shabbat it’s a נולד nolad issue. They
break ערב שבת erev Shabbat because they were once a vessel that
helps them retain their status of a vessel on שבת. Shabbat? When
שבת Shabbat. comes around, what do you need to retain it? It
has to do at least some function. Does it have to do
the original function? That's the position of רבי יהודה, that it needs
that. Presumably רבי מאיר is... I mean רבי מאיר is any function.
But then the question that the גמרא Gemara threw in is to
what degree does context matter, and how much in a particular, you
know, where it is, כרמלית, Carmelit, רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, other types
of context, would it matter whether it’s still considered to be something
that you would still be using or something that you would be
throwing out. Okay, we end the... now the last point of this
ברייתא brayta was about the cover of the oven without a handle.
הי רבי יאשיה משום רבי אליעזר בן יעקב חשיבי תנור ישן שניטלין
בשבת. Hei Rabbi Yoshi mishum Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hashivei tanur yashan
shenitlin beShabbos. So A, that you can use the broken pieces of
an oven, and number two, ועל כיסויו שאינו צריך בית יד, ve'al
kisuyo she'eino tzarich beis yad, that the cover does not need a
handle. אמר אבידא כמאן מטלטלינא האידנא כיסויי דתנורא דמתא מחסיא דאין להם
בית אחיזה? Amar Avida keman mataltelina ha'idna kisuy de'tanuray de'Matza Mechasya de'ein
lahem beis achiza? According to whom do we nowadays move the covers
of the ovens of מתא מחסיא, Matza Mechasya, which was a town
in בבל, Bavel, a city in בבל Bavel that don’t have a
handle? כמאן כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Keman? Ke'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. Which
is all very interesting, but it doesn’t tell us what the issue
is at stake. So we will see, this is the last משנה
of the פרק. perek. Part of the issue at stake here is
that if you have a cover without a handle, to what degree,
you know, especially if like let's say it's a manhole cover, it's
something of a cover of something in the ground, to what degree
does that start leading to בונה boneh concerns? Right? Because without a
handle, it’s not something that’s easily made for removing. So it might
be less of a מוקצה muktseh issue and other types of concerns
as well that feed into the מוקצה muktseh concern. Okay, so we’ll
see more of that at the end of the פרק. perek. Next
משנה. האבן שבקירויה. Ha'even shebakiruyah. קירויה Kiruyah is the name of a
type of hollowed-out gourd that was used for drawing water. Now the
problem with a gourd to use it to draw water is it
might be very good as functioning as an ad hoc, because of
its shape or whatever, but there’s a little problem using a gourd
for drawing water. Any thoughts what the problem would be? It floats.
So what they would do is they would put a rock in
it to weigh it down so they could use it for drawing
water from the well. Is the rock מוקצה muktseh or not? So
אם ממלאין בה ואינה נופלת, im memalin bah ve'einah nofeles, if you
use a gourd and the rock does not float out, so somehow
it’s heavy enough, it’s a tight enough fit, it’s tied down, then
ממלאין בה, memalin bah, you can use this gourd and the rock
is considered part of the vessel. ואם לאו, but if it'll float
out, then it’s not considered part of the vessel and it’s מוקצה
muktzah and אין ממלאין בה, ein memalin bah, you can’t use the
gourd because then you’re moving the מוקצה muktzah rock and the gourd
might be a בסיס basis and so on, and we’re going to
get into discussions of בסיס. basis. זמורה שקשורה בטפיח, Zemora shekeshurah betapiach,
let’s say you have a vine that is tied to a טפיח,
tapiach, to some type, and again, that you would use to draw
water from the well. So if it’s tied to it, ממלאין בה
בשבת, memalin bah beShabbos, you can use it. But if it’s not,
then it’s considered again not a vessel, it’s just considered a random
vine and you can’t use it, you know, again, even if you
made some type of a slip knot or some type of a
thing that wasn't a קשר kesher issue, if you just have a
cut piece of vine lying around the house, it’s מוקצה muktzah unless
you actually use it. Now here is an interesting contrast, and this
is what we’ll get to in
a minute, between this and a שבר כלי, shever kli, right? This
might be just as functional as a שבר כלי. shever kli. But
a שבר כלי shever kli started its life as a כלי. kli
So even as a שבר כלי, shever kli, it more retains its
status of something that is considered to be non-מוקצה muktzah, and usable.
This which never yet became used, it doesn’t get that status just
because you’re maybe planning on using it. You actually have to do
something with it and tie it to the bucket. So this is
going to be a question like using a rock as a paperweight.
שבר כלי, Shever kli, again, started as a כלי kli so it
retains its status more. Taking a piece of nature and turning it
into something usable might require more than just designation, might require actually
using it, doing something to it, and we'll see more about this
in the גמרא. Gemara. Yeah, quickly Rifka and then Michael, but very
quickly.
Yeah, so the second phrase but not the first phrase. Oh, use
it on
שבת?
Shabbos,
Yeah, that’s a good question. Presumably they’re all talking about using it
on שבת. Shabbos I don’t know. But it... yeah, it’s a good
question, right. Right. I don’t know. It’s a good question, yeah. I
don’t know.
In the first case with the אבן *even* that's loose in the
gourd and then it makes the whole thing מוקצה muktzah, *muktza*, both
the אבן *even* and then the gourd, right?
Right, well we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, yeah.
Now, פקק החלון *pkak hachalon*, now this last thing is not so
much a מוקצה muktzah. *muktza* issue, but since we're talking about things
tied to one another then and this will come up also at
the end of the מסכת *masechet* we talk about this. You have
a thing, a stopper for a window. They didn't have like window
shades or whatever, they basically had like these big pieces of wood
or whatever they were that you would
use to fill up the window. So can you do that on
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*? רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer* בזמן שקשור ותלוי
פוקמין בו *bizman shekashur vetalui pokmin bo*. If it is tied, like
the bucket that was tied, so if basically it's tied to the
wall, this stopper, and it's suspended, it's not dragging on the ground,
then you can fill up the window with it, ואם לאו אין
ein פוקמין בו *veim lav ein pokmin bo*, if not you can't.
Why? Because it's more like of a בונה *boneh* concern that then
it's like you're adding something new to the window. But if it's
tied to the wall and it's suspended, it's not even on the
ground, so it's really seen as a piece of the wall as
like part of the shutters of the window, you know, of the
window, then you can fill it up, but otherwise not.
Would you be treating it like a cork in a bottle, would
it be?
Yeah, but that's obviously very, that's less of a בונה *boneh*, here
you're adding it to a structure. So וחכמים אומרים *vechachamim omrim* no,
here it's particularly because you're adding it to a structure. וחכמים אומרים
בין כך ובין כך פוקקין בו *vechachamim omrim bein kach uvein kach
pokin bo*. Oh, you're saying it's מותר *mutar* because it becomes like
that. Okay, yeah. Anyway, the rabbis say regardless you can. So this,
these are like בונה *boneh* concerns when is adding something sort of
on a temporary basis considered בונה *boneh* and how much structurally do
you need it to be sort of demonstrating that it's only temporary
or not? How much does it have to be part of the
structure of the object? So it has to be connected and suspended
and so on. All right, let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* first continuing with the מוקצה muktzah. *muktza* discussion. תנן התם
*Tnan hatam*, we taught over there later in our מסכת *masechet*. אבן
שעל פי החבית *Even sheal pi hachavit*, if you have a stone
on the mouth of a barrel, basically as a stopper, a bottle
stopper, מטה על צדה והיא נופלת *mateh al tzidah vehi nofelet*. You
can tip the barrel and the stone falls off. Okay? So basically
the barrel is not considered a בסיס *basis* and the stone is
מוקצה muktzah. *muktza*, so you tip it and you get to the
stuff in the barrel. We will talk about it. אמר רבה אמר
רב אמי אמר Rav Ami amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Amar Rabba
amar Rav Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan* לא lo, שנו אלא בשוכח *lo
shanu ela beshocheach*. That's only if you forgot and you accidentally left
the stone there. אבל במניח *aval bemaniach*, if you intentionally left the
stone there, נעשה בסיס לדבר האסור *naaseh basis ledavar haasur*, then the
barrel becomes a בסיס *basis*, a support for a מוקצה muktzah *muktza*
stone. So we're not going to focus on בסיס *basis* now, but
the general point is that if you have a מוקצה muktzah *muktza*
object, and by מוקצה muktzah *muktza* I do not mean כלי kli.
שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli shemelachto leissur*, that is כלים *kelim*, that's not מוקצה
muktzah *muktza* just remind you. If you have a מוקצה muktzah, *muktza*
object like a stone or מוקצה muktzah מחמת מיאוס *muktza machamat mius*
or מוקצה muktzah? מחמת חסרון כיס *muktza machamat chisron kis* and you
leave it on a table or some type of a base, בסיס
*basis*, and intentionally leave it there, then the base becomes secondary to
it and the base also becomes מוקצה muktzah *muktza*. If it is
intentionally left there, that's why the whole issue about the candles on
the tray, because the candles are real מוקצה muktzah *muktza*, so you
put something else on the tray so it's not only a בסיס
*basis* for the candles. That's only when it's intentional. So he says
if the stone was intentionally left there, then the barrel becomes מוקצה
muktzah *muktza*. And that's the cover, right? We'll talk about that in
a minute. Okay, but if it was forgotten there, that's when the
barrel is okay and just you tip the stone and you're fine.
I mean you do it, you know, you incidentally move the stone
and the barrel itself is okay. That's what he says. Okay, אמר
רבה מותבינא *Amar Rabba motvina*... I'm sorry, I skipped a line. ורב
יוסף אמר רב אסי אמר Rav Assi amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan.
*VeRav Yosef amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan*. That's what רבה *Rabba*
says in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. Now
רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* says in the name of... I'm
sorry, that was רב אמי Rav Ami, *Rav Ami* in the name
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. Now here's רב אסי *Rav
Assi* in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. לא
שנו אלא בשוכח *Lo shanu ela beshocheach*. You're right, that הלכה *halacha*
is only if you forgot the stone, but in the opposite direction.
אבל במניח *Aval bemaniach*, if you intentionally put the stone there, נעשה
כיסוי לחבית *naaseh kisui lachavit*, you made the stone into a barrel
cover. You made it into a כלי kli? *kli*. It stops being
מוקצה muktzah *muktza*. So what the real question here is not a
debate about בסיס *basis*. The real debate here is, does putting the
stone and using it in a functional way make it into a
כלי kli, *kli*? Okay, so as I said, this is the opposite
issue of the שברי כלי kli, *shivre kli*. There it started as
a כלי kli, *kli* and now it's only like pieces of pottery
and it retains its original status more. Here it starts as a
piece of nature. What do you need to do to turn it
into a כלי kli? *kli*? And is putting it to a use
enough or do you have to somehow change it? So he says
once you use it as a bottle stopper, you've made it into
a כלי kli, *kli*. Okay. אמר רבה מותבינא אשמעתא *Amar Rabba motvina
ashmata*. Now we, I challenge our own position, which is that the
stone remains מוקצה muktzah. *muktza*. That was רבה *Rabba*'s position from our
משנה *mishna*. האבן שבקירויה *Haevan shebekiruya*, אם ממלאים בה ואינה נופלת ממלאים
בה *im memalin bah veeina nofelet memalin bah*.
If you can fill it and the stone doesn't fall out, you
can fill it. And so therefore what do you see? You see
there that a stone can be considered automatically a כלי kli, *kli*
from our... case of the stone in the gourd. So how do
we explain why the stone on the barrel is not a כלי?
kli, ולא היא, Velo hi, but that's not a challenge to our
position. התם כיון דהתקה, Hasam keivan de-hatka, there you did something to
it. You made it tight so it wouldn't fall out, you made
it very tight into the gourd or you tied it down, שוייה
דופן, shavye dofen, you made it a wall of the gourd, you
made it part of the gourd. So the gourd press-in is not
a challenge to me, I could actually say that that's exactly good
because you did something to the stone. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, so רב יוסף says, ומשנינא שמעתא, u'mashnina shmaita, we similarly asked
on our own position that says that you don't have to do
anything. אם לאבן ממלאין בה, Im l'avin memalin bah, if the stone
falls out, you can't fill it. Why is that? Why don't I
say that the stone is put there for a functional purpose? I
say you don't have to do anything to make it a כלי,
kli, why should it be מוקצה muktzah regardless? ולא היא, Velo hi,
but that's you know what that's not a problem. התם כיון דלא
התקה, Hasam keivan delo hatka, there if it's not tight, the problem
isn't that you didn't do something to it, the problem is is
that it's not so functional, בי בטולי בטליה, bei bitulei batlei, you've
negated from considering it a כלי kli because it's going to fall
out. So basically how do you interpret the case of the gourd?
Is the case of the gourd the stone stops being a כלי
kli, because you did something to it? That would be the position
of רב, I forget, רב אמי, Rav Ami, רב אמי, Rav Ami
that you have to do something to it. Or is it or
is it does the stone is not a כלי because it'll fall
out, it's not functional. But if it's functional even without doing anything
to it, it can become a כלי. So what do you need
to make a stone into a כלי? That's the debate. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says במאי קמיפלגי, b'mai kamifligi, what's this debate about?
מר סבר בעינן מעשה ומר סבר לא בעינן מעשה, Mar savar ba'inan
ma'aseh umar savar lo ba'inan ma'aseh, like I said fundamentally when you
take something a piece of nature to turn it into a כלי,
do you need to physically do something to it or is it
enough just to use it? ואזדו לטעמייהו, Va'azdu l'ta'amayhu, they go according
to their reasonings. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי חנינא, De-ki atha
Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Chanina, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came, רב
דימי Rav Dimi was the one who said no not רב דימי
Rav Dimi excuse me, אמר רבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Chanina, in the
name of רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, ואמרי לה אמר רבי זירא אמר
רבי חנינא, v'amri lah amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbi Chanina, פעם אחת
הלך רבי למקום אחד, Pa'am achat halach Rabbi l'makom echad, one time
רבי went to a certain place, ומצא נדבך של אבנים, u'matza nidbach
shel avanim, and he saw like a row of bricks, of stones
excuse me, ואמר לתלמידיו, v'amar l'talmidav, he said to his students, צאו
וחשבו כדי שנשב עליהם למחר, tse'u v'chishvu k'dei she-neshev aleihem l'machar, it
was ערב שבת Erev Shabbat and he said go and think about
it, you know, plan to use them so they won't be מוקצה
muktzah so we can use them tomorrow. They were leftover bricks from
a construction site otherwise they could have just sat on it anyway.
Right. So anyway, right, ולא הצריכן רבי למעשה, velo hitchrichan Rabbi l'ma'aseh,
and he didn't require that they do anything to make them non-מוקצה
muktzah so that seems like a direct proof that you don't need
to do anything, you know, you don't even need to use them,
just you need to think about it. ורבי יוחנן אמר, V'Rabbi Yochanan
amar, but רבי יוחנן says that was the first version, אמר הצריכן
רבי למעשה, amar hitchrichan Rabbi l'ma'aseh, no, רבי did demand that something
be done to it. Now both positions before about what you need
to do the stone were in the name of רבי יוחנן. And
here רבי יוחנן is saying that רבי demanded something be done to
these stones. So what the so מאי אמר להו, mai amar lehu,
what did he demand? What did he say? What did רבי demand?
And now there are two versions of what רבי יוחנן said רבי
said. Okay, רב אמי Rav Ami אמר, now רב אמי who was
the who was the position that said that it needs a real
action done to it to make a stone into a כלי, he
said that that רבי יוחנן said רבי says the following, אמר צאו
ולמדו, amar tse'u v'limdu, go and teach them. No I'm kidding. Go
and arrange them. Okay, so you needed somehow to arrange the stones
in a way that actually made them like a type of a
bench and made them usable. You actually needed to do some type
of a real action to them. Now
I
want to say something. Arranging doesn't sound like an action. It doesn't
sound like any more than putting the stone on the barrel, you're
just moving it and positioning it. So רש״י actually says no, what
he actually said was this, arrange them so that we don't have
to move them on שבת, Shabbos
meaning that he actually said to them they're going to remain
מוקצה, muktzah you're not going to be able you know you've got
to do a real action to change their status, so and you're
not going to do that to them, they're going to remain מוקצה,
muktzah, so if you want to if you want to use them
on שבת Shabbos, you better move them now and get them in
position now because you won't be able to move them on שבת.
Shabbos, Okay so that's what רב אמי said he said, אמר להו.
amar lehu. רב אסי אמר, no, צאו ושפשיפו אמר להו, tse'u v'shifshifu
amar lehu, he just said go and like dust them off from
dirt and that would be enough to designate them and then you
could go ahead and move them on שבת Shabbos and they're not
מוקצה. unmuktzeh. So you see there were versions about whether you needed
to do a real action to them or not, which they weren't
going to do. So according to one that you needed to do
it there wouldn't have been a way to move them on שבת,
Shabbos. and according to the other just some type of trivial thing
to show their use is enough and then they stop being מוקצה.
Okay so איתמר רבי יוסי בן שאול אומר, itmar Rabbi Yosei ben
Shaul omer, it was taught, רבי יוסי בן שאול Rabbi Yosei ben
Shaul says, שורה של קורות הוי, soreh shel koros havei, it was
not stones, it was beams. It was like a pile of beams.
רבי יוחנן בן שאול אומר, Rabbi Yochanan ben Shaul omer, גשרא דספינה
הוי, gishra she-safina havei, it was not only that it was like
a big pole that you use to test the depth of water
for a boat so a boat doesn't get grounded. Right well exactly
what the object was. Now who cares what the object was, stones,
beams, whatever. No it might make a the difference. מאן man דאמר
damar גישוש, gishush, if you say that it was this pole used
for testing depth, כל kol שכן sheken צררי, tzrari, he would certainly
agree that the same would be true about a pile of beans.
ומה uma מאן man דאמר סובר, sovar, but the one who said
a pile of beans, אבל גישוש, gishush, if it was this type
of a pole, קפי kapi ליה, lei, then that would be real
מוקצה. Then it would be something that nobody would want anybody to
use because you'd break it, it's a very valuable, you know, type
of a כלי, this big thing. So here according to these versions,
it wasn't the problem that it was stones and pieces of nature,
and how do you take a piece of nature and make it
a כלי? It was a question about whether it was like construction
material like we had before, which maybe the issue is different. On
the one hand it's easier to be a כלי, but on the
other hand it might be something that's מוקצה because you don't want
anybody fooling with it. Okay, so that raises different concerns. I understand.
So that raises different concerns, again, is the issue about that it's
not a כלי, how do you make it a כלי, or is
the issue it is a כלי, but maybe it's something that you
want people to keep hands off of, two very different versions. And
I do want to say an important thing here besides the question
of what do you need to turn a stone into a paperweight,
you know, or into a doorstop? Do you can you just use
it or do you have to shine it and do you know,
do a מעשה to it? That's the debate we just saw. But
the interesting thing also was he said, do something so we can
sit on it. So what does that mean so we can sit
on it? So רש״י says it means that we're gonna want to
move it on שבת, Shabbat. right? So if we're gonna want to
move it in order to sit on it, so it's a מוקצה
concern. But the רשב״א Rashba brings an opinion that says מוקצה could
be an issue even without moving. Now, not like kids think like
מוקצה is like cooties and you can't touch מוקצה, okay, but using
מוקצה without moving it, is that a problem? Can you sit on
מוקצה? Can you sit on a car? Okay, here's right? Is מוקצה
only moving or is מוקצה even using? So according to one version,
the רשב״א Rashba says that the problem here was not that they
would have to move it in order to sit on it, but
you couldn't sit on it if it's מוקצה because you can't use
מוקצה even if you don't move מוקצה. We basically don't פסקן pasken
that way, we פסקן pasken that מוקצה is about moving, but that
is an interesting debate based on how you read this גמרא. Gemara
Yeah, like I mean a rock big enough to sit on isn't
so easy to move, so maybe the רשב״א Rashba should only apply
that to things that you can't move. Oh, could be, could be,
but I don't know, it's a good question, but he seems to
make it as a general issue. Okay, let's try to get just
read to the next two dots. זמורה zmora שקשורה, shekshurah, so this
is about the vine connected to the bucket and it has to
be tied, similar to the stone has to have been put to
use before שבת in order to make it a vessel. קשורה kshurah
אם לא קשורה kshurah לא, only if it's tied, not if it's
not tied. לימא leima מתניתין matnitin דלא delo רבן Rabban שמעון Shimon
בן ben גמליאל, Gamliel, may this not be like רבן Rabban שמעון
Shimon בן ben גמליאל, Gamliel, דתנן, a תנא tanna taught in a
ברייתא. braisa. חריות chariyot של דקל dekel שגיררן shegigeran לעצים, le-eitzim, you
have, you know, parts of a staff of a palm tree that
you have carved and chopped, you know, to use for wood. ונימלך
venimalach עליהן aleihen לישיבה, lishiva, and then you decide you know what,
I'm gonna use them to sit on. So again, it's a type
of a thing like this vine that was a part of nature,
it was going to be something that wasn't a vessel, it was
going to be used as firewood, and now you want to make
it a vessel and for שבת. What do you need? Is it
enough to think about it? Do you have to actually go ahead
and do something to it? It's very similar to the stone issue
and it's very interesting that the גמרא Gemara doesn't put it in
conversation. It's slightly different because here presumably you've done something to it
already, you've cut the vine, you've cut these pieces of the palm,
but you did something to it, but what you did didn't make
it a vessel yet. You're turning it into firewood and now you
want to make it a vessel, so maybe it's in slightly its
own category, maybe you need less than you would need by the
stone which is a random piece of nature. Okay, so what do
you need to do? So צריך tzarich לקשור, likshor, so if you
want to turn these pieces into like you have to tie them
in order it's not enough to think about them. רבן Rabban שמעון
Shimon בן ben גמליאל Gamliel אומר אין צריך tzarich לקשור, likshor, no,
it's enough just to designate them. So again, he might not say
it by the stone, but here that you've already cut it and
taken control over it, maybe it's enough just to think about it.
So presumably he would say the same by this vine with the
bucket. אמר רב ששת Sheshet אפילו תימא teima רבן Rabban שמעון Shimon
בן ben גמליאל, Gamliel, no, even רבן Rabban שמעון Shimon בן ben
גמליאל Gamliel would say the vine and the bucket is different. הכא
hacha במאי bemai עסקינן, askinan, what are we talking about? במחוברת bemichuberet
באביה. be-aviha. It's not a just a מוקצה issue. The vine is
still attached, okay, it's got to be a really long vine that
you could tie the bucket to it and lower it down the
well. So that's the issue. And because it's attached to the ground,
it's a real that's why it's a bigger מוקצה issue. Of course
that's pretty amazing that you get it out of being מוקצה by
tying it to a bucket. So the גמרא says one minute, forget
מוקצה, אי הכי קמשתמש kamishtamesh במחובר bemichubar לקרקע, lekarka, you're not allowed
to use things that are attached to the ground because we're afraid
you'll come to break them off, you know, break off a twig
and so on. So even if it is tied to the bucket,
why is it permitted? So the גמרא says למטה lemata
מג׳, migimmel, it's within three of the ground. If it's within But
that's only things, interestingly, that are attached, but are higher than the
ground, more than three, so you might forget that they're attached.
If it's right close to the ground, you're actually allowed to use
it. Okay, yeah, actually that's true. Okay, well again, this'll get, we'll
get to that stuff. Anyway, the basic point here is because it's
attached, it's harder to make it unמוקצה. רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi
amar אפילו תימא בתלושה, afilu teima bitlusha, even if it's detached, גזירה
שמא יקטום, gezeira shema yikto, we might demand here more because if
we allow you to use a detached one, you'll come around next
time and you'll break a piece off from something growing. So we
might here demand more that you make it, you put it and
you start using it in a functional way and tie it to
the vessel already from before שבת. But again, the key here is,
is about what do you need to take a, on the one
hand you have something that was a כלי and then became shards,
and that retains its status more, and then you're going in the
opposite direction taking pieces of nature like stones and vines and so
on and turning them into a כלי, and that might be hard,
harder to get them into that category. Is it enough to start
using them? Do you have to physically change them, do something to
them, and so on? And those are the various debates that we
have seen.